All right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is מ"ט. Mem
Tet. We're drawing to an end of the third פרק, perek, and
we start with the top of מ"ט עמוד א', Mem Tet Amud
Aleph, the משנה. Mishnah. ארבעה עשר שחל להיות בשבת. Arba'asar she'chal lihyot
b'Shabbat. If the 14th is on שבת, Shabbat, so, you know, nowadays
that's like a subspecialty of the areas of הלכות פסח, Hilchot Pesach,
ארבעה עשר שחל להיות בשבת. Arba'asar she'chal lihyot b'Shabbat. Right now you
can get, you know, big like halachic monographs, like works on tiny
little areas of הלכה. halachah. You know, this is like one סימן
siman in the שלחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, but there's actually a ספר
sefer out there that's on ארבעה עשר שחל להיות בשבת. Arba'asar she'chal
lihyot b'Shabbat. ערב פסח שחל להיות בערב שבת, Erev Pesach she'chal lihyot
b'Erev Shabbat, ארבעה עשר שחל להיות בשבת Arba'asar she'chal lihyot b'Shabbat because
you can't do the ביעור bi'ur on ערב פסח Erev Pesach itself,
that's one issue. And the other issue, which doesn't get discussed in
our משנה, mishnah, is how do you have שלש סעודות? shalosh seudot?
Right, because you're, you know, and how do you deal with the
issue about, you know, about כל... kol... you know, about because you're
not supposed to eat the morning of the 14th, you can still
have חמץ, chametz, but by the afternoon you can't, and you're not
allowed to eat מצה matzah on ערב פסח. Erev Pesach. מצה עשירה.
matzah ashirah. So you have מצה עשירה. matzah ashirah. Can you make
a המוציא Hamotzi on מצה עשירה? matzah ashirah? Anyway, you can imagine
that these are the major issues עומדים ברומו של עולם. omdim b'rumo
shel olam.
So that's what our משנה mishnah addresses itself to.
Rumo, much it's discussed it with, because there's a משנה... mishnah...
I know, it's very... that's my point. I mean, obviously it's a
halachic issue that needs to be addressed, but let's take a look
at the treatment it gets in the גמרא. Gemara. ארבעה
עשר שחל להיות בשבת, Arba'asar she'chal lihyot b'Shabbat, if the 14th falls
out on שבת, Shabbat, מבערין את הכל מלפני השבת, m'va'arin et hakol
milifnei haShabbat, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. So you get rid
of everything ערב שבת Erev Shabbat because you don't know if you'll
have an opportunity to get rid of it on שבת. Shabbat. So
what's the halachic concern, besides telling us that that's a good idea?
The possible halachic concern would be a waste of food, and as
we're about to see, we're always dealing with the possibility that some
of your stuff is תרומה. terumah. So you're destroying תרומה terumah which
otherwise could be eaten. So the concern though about חמץ chametz outweighs.
That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, the
חכמים Chachamim say, בזמנו, bizmano, wait, do everything on the 14th. We
assume you'll find someone to get it done, you'll find some way
to handle it. בזמנו. bizmano.
Yeah, I mean then you'll wind up wasting תרומה, terumah, you know,
then you'll find, then you're just delaying it. Then not only are
you being מחלל שבת, mechalel Shabbat, but then also it's more, you
know, it's more difficult. It's easier to throw something in a fire.
It's more difficult to find other ways of destroying it.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah would agree with רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir since
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah is the one that holds that it's שריפה.
sereifah. But now you're not doing it בזמנו. bizmano.
Well, that's a good point, you know, I don't know, and you
know, so who are the חכמים Chachamim of רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir?
Right, it can't be רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah because רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehudah says בשריפה. bi'sreifah. So it's interesting that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
is the one that דווקא davka says ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, because
you're right, if you wait till שבת, Shabbat, you don't have the
option of שריפה. sereifah. רבי אליעזר בר צדוק אומר תרומה מלפני השבת
וחולין בזמנה. Rabbi Eliezer bar Tzadok omer terumah milifnei haShabbat vechullin bizmana.
Now this is a little ironic. He says do the תרומה terumah
ערב שבת Erev Shabbat
and the חולין chullin on שבת. Shabbat. Now the תרומה terumah is
the one you would think you most want to be careful not
to destroy without... unless you need to, unless there's no option. But
if you wait till שבת, Shabbat, what's the problem?
תרומה, terumah, there's not so many people available to eat it. חולין,
chullin, there's a lot of people available to eat it. So you
can be more confident that you can hold on to your חמץ
chametz and your חולין chullin and get rid of it on שבת.
Shabbat. תרומה terumah less so. And again, this is assuming that, you
know, that opportunities for destroying it on שבת Shabbat are less than
they would be during the week.
If you're a כהן, Kohen, would this change? If you're...
it's... you know, that gets to the issue before that רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva said about לא כל האנשים שוות. lo kol anashim shavot.
If proportional to how much תרומה terumah do you have and how
many כהנים Kohanim do you have in the house, obviously the things
could be different.
You know, so...
I don't know. I don't know. Okay, let's see the גמרא. Gemara.
תניא. Tanya.
Write that down, לא כל האנשים שוות. lo kol anashim shavot.
All right, תניא. Tanya. It's a... I find it's a very good
line when you're dating, you know, or something. Anyway, תניא. Tanya. רבי
אליעזר בר צדוק אומר פעם אחת שבת אבא, Rabbi Eliezer bar Tzadok
omer pa'am achat shabat Abba, so one time my father spent the
שבת Shabbat or it might mean he... yeah, he spent the שבת
Shabbat ביבנה, b'Yavneh, in יבנה. Yavneh. It happened to be שבת ערב
פסח. Shabbat Erev Pesach. So it looked like he was going to
be spending פסח Pesach in יבנה Yavneh as well. And יבנה Yavneh
was the city where the נשיא Nasi lived. Right? רבי Rebbi and
so on. וחלה ארבעה עשר להיות בשבת, Vechal Arba'asar lihyot b'Shabbat, and
the 14th fell out that week on שבת. Shabbat. ובא זונין ממונה
של רבן גמליאל, Uba Zonin memuneh shel Rabban Gamliel, זונין, Zonin, who
was רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel's officer, somehow his like servant, his... you
know, some important person in his of his retinue, he came. ואמר,
V'amar, and he said, הגיע עת לבער את החמץ. higia et l'va'er
et hachametz. He started making announcements apparently throughout the city of יבנה.
Yavneh. Time to destroy your חמץ chametz on שבת. Shabbat. Presumably, yes.
Well, it's not clear, you know. You could read it that way.
You could read it
that way. Is it he was spending... Right now we know that
רבי אליעזר בן צדוק Rabbi Eliezer ben Zadok in the משנה Mishna
says, right, חולין בזמנן. Chulin Bizmanan. So it makes sense therefore that
he's saying חולין Chulin is on
שבת Shabbat itself and he's giving as evidence this story of what
happened in יבנה. Yavne. That it was שבת Shabbat and on שבת
Shabbat he said time to destroy your חמץ, chametz, right, והלכתי אחר
אבא וביערנו את החמץ. v'alachti achar Abba u'viarnu et hachametz. I followed
my father and we destroyed the חמץ. chametz. But again, it's very
confusing because destroyed brings to your mind an image of like burning
the חמץ. chametz. So if it's שבת, Shabbat, you're not destroying. It
could be והלכנו אחר אבא ואכלנו את החמץ v'halachnu achar Abba v'achalnu
et hachametz or something. So again, presumably it's to support his position
of חולין בזמנן, Chulin Bizmanan, but the phrase ביערנו את החמץ biarnu
et hachametz is a little strange. Would have hoped for a little
more specificity. Okay, although it is true in the משנה Mishna itself
it says מבערים את הכל, mevaarim et hakol, and he says no,
מבערים את החולין בשבת, mevaarim et hachulin b'Shabbat, but presumably the מבערים
בשבת mevaarim b'Shabbat means by eating it. Okay.
Do you know of other issues that you mentioned or discussed elsewhere
in the גמרא Gemara or what about like...
No, discussed by the פוסקים. Poskim. Okay, so the משנה, Mishna, next
משנה. Mishna. ההולך לשחוט, Haholech lishchot, again it's an interesting collection of
things. Remember what we had been discussing, right? We had been discussing
how do you make the bread so that it doesn't become חמץ?
chametz? We discussed like these unusual cases of כיצד מבערים, keitzad mevaarim,
חלה בטומאה, challah b'tumah, או כיצד
מפרישין חלה בטומאה. o keitzad mafrishin challah b'tumah. And now we get
to another issue which gets back to the way discussion in the
beginning of the מסכת Masechet about owning your חמץ chametz and getting
rid of your חמץ. chametz. So let's take a look. I mean
in a way it's connected because we're talking about getting rid, burning,
destroying, and so on. But so the last two משניות Mishnayot here
are connected, but how, you know, and I guess I'm just sort
of saying like, you know, the או ישרף o yisaref is also
about destroying the חמץ, chametz, but
so it's all somewhat connected to the concern about making sure you're
not owning חמץ, chametz, you know, even the כיצד מפרישין חלה בטומאה
keitzad mafrishin challah b'tumah is how do you make sure that you
destroy it and you don't own it. So there is a theme
here about these משניות Mishnayot here at the end getting back to
the earlier theme of destroying your חמץ chametz and making sure you
don't own it. So let's take a look. ההולך לשחוט את הפסח,
Haholech lishchot et hapesach, somebody is going, it's the 14th and you're
going to שחט shecht the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. What else should
you be doing on ערב פסח? Erev Pesach? Perfect thing. ולמול את
בנו, U'lamol et bno, and also it happens, it could be an
or and an or and. You know, or but today's your son's
ברית מילה. bris milah. ולאכול סעודת אירוסין בבית חמיו, V'leechol seudat eirusin
b'veit chamiv, or and and, you could make it all and. Or
you happen to have gotten אירוסין eirusin today, you have your or
a day ago or whatever, you happen to have just done קדושין
kiddushin and not yet נשואין. nissuin. You're not married, you're not yet
living with your new wife, but you're officially married. No,
right, I know, but אירוסין eirusin means it's not yet נשואין, nissuin,
so you're not yet living together, but you are married, you had
קדושין, kiddushin, and apparently you would go and you'd have a party
after the קדושין kiddushin and it wouldn't be like the week of
שבע ברכות, sheva brachot, but there would be a party that you
would have
after קדושין kiddushin and you'd have it at the father-in-law's house and
you're going to do that and that was considered to be a
מצוה. mitzvah. I should say by the way that although, you know,
אין מערבין שמחה בשמחה, ein mearvin simcha b'simcha, and you're not allowed
to get married on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, excuse me, you are
allowed to get married, you're not allowed to have נשואין nissuin on
חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, but you're allowed to have קדושין. kiddushin. One
reason is שמא יקדמנו אחר. shema yikadmenu acher. Okay, but the other
reason is also, is also that קדושין kiddushin technically is not a
שמחה, simcha, right? The ברכות brachot of שבע ברכות sheva brachot are
said with the נשואין, nissuin, it's not yet the lived experience of
living together. But the הלכה halacha is the one thing you can't
do on חול המועד Chol HaMoed is have סעודת אירוסין בבית חמיו.
seudat eirusin b'veit chamiv. That was a special thing, a special meal
they had after the אירוסין eirusin which was particularly seen as a
מצוה mitzvah and seen as something very much of an issue of
שמחה. simcha. And anyway, so that does have status in other places
of הלכה. halacha. So here we're doing it that you're going to
do this מצוה. mitzvah. One minute, let's get to the end of
the thought. You're going to do this מצוה. mitzvah. ונזכר שיש לו
חמץ בתוך ביתו. V'nizkar sheyesh lo chametz b'toch beito. Oh my god,
I forgot to get rid of my חמץ. chametz. What am I
supposed to do? אם יכול לחזור ולבער, Im yachol lachzor u'lvaer, if
you can get back to your house and destroy it while it's
still the, you know,
while
it's, well, no, let's see.
לחזור ולבער ולחזור למצותו, Lachzor u'lvaer v'lachzor l'mitzvato, to go and to
destroy it and to come back and do your מצוה. mitzvah. So
you can do it without it interfering with your performance of the
מצוה. mitzvah.
Right, you'd have to have
שחט shechted the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Otherwise it'd be too late
to מבער. mevaer. That's true, right, exactly. So obviously you still have
time. I mean, look, even if it's פסח, Pesach, you destroy your
חמץ chametz if you still have it, but obviously it's still ערב
פסח. Erev Pesach. Anyway, if you can do it and get back
and still do your מצוה mitzvah without interfering with your מצוה, mitzvah,
then יחזור ויבער, yachzor v'yvaer, then go ahead and do it. ואם
לאו, V'im lav, and if you can't, מבטלו בלבו. mevatlo b'libo. You
just do ביטול. bittul. So here the משנה, Mishna, the first משנה,
Mishna, if you've been paying attention since the beginning of the פרק,
Perek, we've always talked about burning and destroying your חמץ. chametz. The
first time the idea of ביטול bittul occurs is the last משנה
Mishna of the third פרק Perek when we're... basically wrapping up issues
of חמץ, chametz, and we say if you have no option, reasonable
option of going back and doing ביעור, biur, we allow you to
do ביטול. bittul. So it's important to note, you know, that although
the the right the first רש"י Rashi in the מסכת masechet says
why do you do, you know, בדיקת חמץ לאור הנר, bedikat chametz
l'or haner, right? אור לארבעה עשר בודקין את החמץ לאור הנר. or
l'arba'ah asar bodkin et hachametz l'or haner. Why do you do it?
רש"י Rashi says not to be עובר over on בל יראה ובל
ימצא. bal yira'eh ubal yimatzei. So תוספות Tosafot says what do you
mean not to be עובר over on בל יראה ובל ימצא? bal
yira'eh ubal yimatzei? The רב rav says הבודק צריך שיבטל. habodek tzarich
sheyivatel. So everybody's doing ביטול. bittul. So if everybody's doing ביטול, bittul,
nobody's being עובר over on בל יראה ובל ימצא. bal yira'eh ubal
yimatzei. Why do you need to do בדיקה bedikah as well? And
he gives whatever reason he gives, like it's a you know, what,
it's דרבנן derabbanan and it's you know you might find the חמץ
chametz and you'll come to eat it. Or if the תורה Torah
is מחמיר machmir about בל יראה ובל ימצא, bal yira'eh ubal yimatzei,
we're going to be מחמיר machmir even if you've done your ביטול.
bittul. Anyway, that's תוספות'ס Tosafot's question. But the answer is רש"י Rashi
is right, in the משנה Mishna you never did ביטול. bittul. In
the משנה Mishna you did בדיקה bedikah and you did ביעור biur
not to be עובר over on בל יראה ובל ימצא. bal yira'eh
ubal yimatzei. ביטול bittul was a sort of was a last resort
for extenuating circumstances. Because we all know you do ביטול bittul it
becomes like a farce. So the חז"ל Chazal even though technically ביטול
bittul would have worked, in the time of the משנה Mishna they
only allowed it in extenuating circumstances. And therefore the reason for בדיקה
bedikah and ביעור biur was it was being done without ביטול bittul
and it was not to be עובר over on בל יראה ובל
ימצא. bal yira'eh ubal yimatzei. Then in the time of the אמוראים
Amoraim was introduced the idea הבודק צריך שיבטל. habodek tzarich sheyivatel. And
then the question comes oh well now and you know like belts
and suspenders. You know what? If ביטול bittul works then we might
as well always just do it as a backup anyway. Even if
you're doing בדיקה bedikah go ahead and do ביטול bittul in case
you missed something. It's a great backup. Okay, it's a reasonable idea.
That comes up in the time of the אמוראים. Amoraim. Everybody should
do ביטול. bittul. But then the question is so why are we
bothering doing בדיקה? bedikah? Okay, and that's the issue that תוספות Tosafot
deals with at the beginning but it's important to note the historical
development of the use of ביטול. bittul.
So I assume this משנה Mishna is not on שבת. Shabbat.
Right, this is a normal right correct
you're not reading it in
a context no no no no it's not on שבת. Shabbat. I
mean you have a similar scenario on שבת Shabbat because you could
go back and eat your חמץ chametz if there's enough time and
if it's before you know noon or eleven or whatever but it's
not relating specifically to שבת. Shabbat. You had a question before?
Yeah I just want to make sure I get this. So what
you're saying is really on a Mishnaic level no one's doing any
ביטול bittul because you said you don't want it to be a
farce. But then it was although ביטול bittul was mentioned over here
it's it's a last.
It's a last resort. We allow you yes it does technically work
but we don't want to use it until we unless we.
Because ביטול מדאורייתא סגי bittul mideoraita sagi is what the גמרא'ס Gemara's
been saying and then we just we just had it anyway because
it's a good backup.
Exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says so that's if you're
doing a מצוה mitzvah you make the חשבון cheshbon about whether you
can go and do it and come back and do your מצוה
mitzvah or not or will it interfere with it. Now by the
way I should mention how does this fit into a general principle
of עוסק במצוה פטור מן המצוה? osek bemitzvah patur min hamitzvah? Because
this is not just פטור מן המצוה patur min hamitzvah of a
מצוה mitzvah of ביעור biur there's a problem of the בל יראה
ובל ימצא bal yira'eh ubal yimatzei of a לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh.
Normally we say עוסק במצוה פטור מן המצוה osek bemitzvah patur min
hamitzvah it's actually a you know some some debate in the ראשונים
Rishonim but generally we don't say oh I should drop this מצוה
mitzvah and go do the other one because I can always come
back and do this one. Although this is discussed what if the
מצוה mitzvah you're doing is a מצוה שאינה עוברת mitzvah she'einah overet
and the other מצוה mitzvah is a מצוה עוברת? mitzvah overet? Do
you interrupt this to do the other one and therefore get both?
Or no the whole point of it is is that you know
is that even if the other one is a is a מצוה
עוברת mitzvah overet you keep on doing the one that you're doing
because that you're not obligated to attend to the other one.
So anyway that's an issue by עוסק במצוה פטור מן המצוה osek
bemitzvah patur min hamitzvah but this is a little bit less relevant
here because here it's not just a מצוה mitzvah of ביעור biur
here it actually is a לא תעשה lo ta'aseh of owning the
חמץ chametz and therefore it raises you know even more serious issues.
So as long as you can get back as long as you
have time to get back to what you're doing you do it.
If not you do ביטול. bittul. Okay. להציל מן הנכרי ומן הנהר
ומן הליסטין ומן הדליקה lehatzil min hanochri umin hanahar umin halistin umin
hadeleikah let's say what you're going to do ומן המפולת umin hamapolet
what you're going to do is not to do a סתם stam
a מצוה mitzvah you're going to actually save people who are in
danger that there are non-Jews attacking it's a מצוה mitzvah but it's
more than a מצוה. mitzvah. Non-Jews that are attacking the city or
there's a river that's about to flood or there's bandits or there's
a fire or there's a building that collapsed and it's all hands
on deck they need everybody to come and help. So in those
cases יבטל בלבו. yevatel belibo. Just do ביטול. bittul. Don't even start
having the חשבון cheshbon of oh well I can go back and
be back and you know what the river won't have gotten that
high by the time I'm back. No, if we're dealing with a
question about risk of life and of safety and whatnot then don't
do any חשבון cheshbon even if you think you'll have time to
come back. That's the way this is different. You go and you
do that and you just do ביטול. bittul. Now
ולשבות שביתת הרשות velishbot shevitat hareshut let's say however if it's the
opposite if you're going not there so we had a normal מצוה,
mitzvah, we had a מצוה mitzvah of saving people, and now we
have something which is a total non-מצוה. mitzvah. Okay, you're going to
spend your שבת Shabbat the way רש"י Rashi says it means that
you're going to put out an עירוב תחומין. eruv techumin. But תוספות
Tosfos says no it just means that you're going because you want
to spend שבת Shabbos and יום טוב Yom Tov and you want
to go to your parents or you want to go to your
kids' place for יום טוב. Yom Tov. So you're on a trip
because that's where you're going for יום טוב, Yom Tov, you know,
you're going to spend יום טוב Yom Tov in wherever, in Maine.
So that's where you're going and you remember after you're all in
the car and you're all packed up and you're two miles already
on the highway you remember oh my God we forgot to do
ביעור. biyur. So what do you do? So יחזור מיד, yachzor miyad,
in that case since it's only a רשות reshus then it's not
a question of oh can I get back do the ביעור biyur
and get still go where I'm going before it becomes יום טוב?
Yom Tov? You know what? Even if you can't tough luck. It's
only a רשות reshus what you're doing and you got a מצוה
mitzvah of ביעור חמץ biyur chametz so you gotta go back and
destroy your חמץ. chametz. Now of course if that scenario really happened
the way I described it it would really be a מצוה mitzvah
anyway because right now you have no food cooked nothing prepared so
if you go and you wind up staying home it's going to
be a serious compromise of your שמחת יום טוב Simchas Yom Tov
you know. So we have to but in a scenario where it's
just נעבעך nebach I won't be able to see be with my
friends but in the end you can stay home and you'll also
work things out then this is actually saying that's just a רשות
reshus it's not a מצוה mitzvah and you gotta go back even
though ביטול bittul is possible. So you really see in the משנה
Mishna how demanding we were to really destroy the חמץ chametz before
we at a time when ביטול bittul was a last resort. וכן
vechein so that's about
חמץ. chametz. Similarly מי שיצא מירושלים ונזכר שיש בידו בשר קודש mi
sheyatza mi-Yerushalayim ve-nizkar she-yesh be-yado basar kodesh here's another case where it's
a question about do I have to go back or not? You
left ירושלים Yerushalayim and you realized that you had some שלמים shelumim
meat that you hadn't finished and you had some שלמים shelumim meat
still in your knapsack okay and you left ירושלים Yerushalayim so now
that שלמים shelumim meat has become פסול. pasul. So the הלכה halacha
is you're supposed to go back and destroy it in ירושלים Yerushalayim
or in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So אם עבר צופים im
avar Tzofim if you've passed צופים Tzofim so צופים Tzofim what does
that mean? Does it mean הר צופים? Har Tzofim? It means רש"י
Rashi says it's a name of a place תוספות Tosfos says it
describes a circumference any place outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim from where you
are in line of sight of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So according to תוספות
Tosfos what it means is you passed a place where you no
longer can see
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. שורפו במקומו sorfo bimkomo so then just burn it wherever
you are.
ואם לאו ve-im lav you're not מטריח matriach
him to go back to ירושלים Yerushalayim and burn it there. But
if you're not if you're still within line of sight חוזר ושורפו
לפני הבירה chozer ve-sorfo lifnei ha-birah you go back and you burn
it in the presence of the בירה birah the castle what there's
a debate what that means but presumably means on or near the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash מעצי המערכה me-atzei ha-maaracha and you use the
wood from the that's dedicated for the altar. Now
תוספות Tosfos says if you remember רש"י Rashi refers to an earlier
גמרא Gemara that says at any time the קרבן korban becomes
פסול pasul you burn it בקודש bakodesh בקודש באש תשרף. bakodesh baesh
tisaref. קודש שפסולה בקודש טעונה שרפה kodesh she-psulah bakodesh teunah sereifah and
you burn it במקום קדוש. bi-makom kadosh. תוספות Tosfos says however there's
a problem because if that were true how would we allow you
to not go back to ירושלים Yerushalayim meaning by the חמץ chametz
at least we could say do ביטול bittul but if there's really
a מצוה mitzvah to burn it in ירושלים Yerushalayim or in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash how are we allowed? So תוספות Tosfos says
the מצוה mitzvah to burn things in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
that become פסול pasul are קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodoshim. This is קדשים
קלים kodshim kalim which could be eaten by a normal person not
a כהן kohen in all of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So because that type
of a thing doesn't even if you take it out of ירושלים
Yerushalayim technically doesn't have to be burned in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So we
can be lenient when we need to be. But there's still the
חז"ל Chazal wanted you to burn it so not to confuse things
and burn it in or near the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and
we'll make you do that if you're still within line of sight.
עד כמה הן חוזרין ad kama hein chozrin for how much food
would you have to go back whether it's to destroy חמץ chametz
or destroy the meat of your קרבן korban that became פסול? pasul?
רבי מאיר
אומר זה וזה כביצה Rebbe Meir omer zeh ve-zeh ke-beitza it's a
כביצה ke-beitza for both. רבי יהודה אומר זה וזה כזית Rebbe Yehudah
omer zeh ve-zeh ke-zayis it's a כזית ke-zayis for both. We'll see
what this debate is in the גמרא. Gemara. וחכמים אומרים ve-Chachamim omrim
the חכמים Chachamim say בשר קודש בכזית וחמץ כביצה basar kodesh be-khazayis
ve-chametz ke-beitza the meat we go by a כזית ke-zayis חמץ chametz
by a כביצה. ke-beitza. The גמרא Gemara never explains it will explain
רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir and רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehudah it never explains
the חכמים. Chachamim. So תוספות Tosfos explains the חכמים Chachamim why are
we more lenient why are we more strict by the meat of
a קרבן korban and lenient by חמץ? chametz? חמץ chametz you don't
go back and burn till it's a כביצה. ke-beitza. תוספות Tosfos says
because again חמץ chametz has a backup חמץ chametz you could always
do ביטול. bittul. So therefore because of that backup at least according
to the חכמים Chachamim even the minimum sizes will be more lenient.
Let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara yes.
So a couple of things. One is so the day that you
brought a קרבן korban isn't that also like a יום טוב Yom
Tov for you? And if so and didn't you say this thing
of אין מערבין שמחה בשמחה? ein mearvin simcha be-simcha? So how can
there be a סעודת אירוסין Seudas Erusin on
ערב פסח? Erev Pesach? Because you're going to eat a סעודת אירוסין
Seudas Erusin and then no it's not.
Interesting. I don't know if we would apply that to the day
of bringing the קרבן פסח korban Pesach it's not a personal קרבן.
korban.
And the סעודת אירוסין Seudas Erusin yeah that's interesting. Yeah I don't
know. And I don't know if we apply אין מערבין שמחה בשמחה
ein mearvin simcha be-simcha to that personal יום טוב Yom Tov anyway
even when you did bring a קרבן. korban. It's an interesting question
I don't know if anybody talks about it.
And the other question is in contrast to the first part where
you’re actually doing a מצווה Mitzvah and then you’re like, oh shoot,
I have this חמץ Chametz at home, the יציאה מירושלים Tzeis miYerushalayim
and you know you have to go back and all that, that’s
not a function of why you’re going out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Is
there a difference if a...
Yeah, that’s an excellent point that here, that’s an excellent point that
as opposed to, I didn’t note that, but as opposed to the
contrast to the last case in the משנה, Mishnah, חמץ, Chametz, that
when you’re going for רשות, Reshus, we always make you go back,
no matter how far you’ve left home, we always make you turn
around and go back. Here you’re leaving for רשות Reshus presumably and
we allow you not to go back. So that’s an excellent point.
Presumably the difference is exactly what we’ve been saying is that, no,
actually it works the opposite way. I was going to say that
by חמץ Chametz you have ביטול, Bittul, but if anything that should
be why it should be more lenient.
Yeah, you make an excellent point. Makes an excellent point that in
the חמץ Chametz case when you’re leaving ברשות biReshus we insist you
go back and here we actually presumably you’re leaving ברשות biReshus and
we’ll be lenient depending on how big of a טרחא Tircha it
is. I have to see. Okay, let’s get back to that. Okay,
we’re not going to get to the קדשים Kodshim case till the
very end of today, so hopefully I’ll have an answer for you
tomorrow.
Sorry to do this but just as a thing that I missed
last time, the פדיון הנכרי Pidyon haNochri and the נהר Nahar etc.,
that’s like to save your own life and...
No, or other people’s, but the point is if it’s not סתם
Stam a מצווה Mitzvah if you’re saving people’s lives then you don’t
start making a חשבון Cheshbon of, oh, you know, I can get
back in time. Right, exactly. Oh, you know, the river probably won’t,
the fire won’t have spread too far by the time I come
back.
That’s to save your property though, that’s being...
Right, but presumably it’s, you know, anything that has a potential risk
of safety as to people’s lives. I don’t think it also has
to be פיקוח נפש, Pikuach Nefesh, let’s say, oh, he’s just going
to get his arm burnt but he won’t die.
No, the basement will get flooded, I mean...
Right, that might be different. All right, it’s a good question. So
let’s take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. ורמינהו, u’Reminhu, asks the גמרא Gemara on this, ההולך לאכול
סעודת אירוסין בבית חמיו ולשבות שביתת הרשות. haHolech leechol Seudas Erusin b’veis
Chamiv v’lishbos Shvisas haReshus. So it says if you’re going to, this
ברייתא Baraita puts the סעודת אירוסין, Seudas Erusin, right, the party after
the הקידושין, Kiddushin, in the father-in-law’s house to in the רשות Reshus
category. Because it says if you’re going to have this type of
a meal in your father-in-law’s house or to spend שבת Shabbos somewhere
for discretion, not out of a מצווה, Mitzvah, then יחזור מיד Yachzor
Miyad you have to go back. So it considers it to be
not a מצווה Mitzvah this סעודת אירוסין. Seudas Erusin.
And that’s a קשיא.
Kashya. אמר רבי יוחנן לא קשיא. Amar Rabbi Yochanan Lo Kashya. הא
רבי יהודה הא רבי יוסי. Ha Reb Yehuda Ha Reb Yosi. It’s
a debate whether this סעודת אירוסין Seudas Erusin is a מצווה Mitzvah
or not, a debate between רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda and רבי יוסי.
Reb Yosi. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in the ברייתא, Baraita, סעודת אירוסין
רשות דברי רבי יהודה. Seudas Erusin Reshus Divrei Reb Yehuda. רבי יהודה
Reb Yehuda says it’s a רשות, Reshus, it’s a מנהג, Minhag, it’s
whatever, it’s all very lovely but there’s no מצווה Mitzvah to do
it. רבי יוסי אומר מצווה, Reb Yosi Omer Mitzvah, it’s a מצווה.
Mitzvah. It’s very funny like what מצווה? Mitzvah? Presumably a דרבנן d’Rabanan
מצווה Mitzvah the same way a lot of things, you know, שבע
ברכות Sheva Brachos and all those things.
רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda had a good relationship with his father-in-law and
רבי יוסי Reb Yosi didn’t have a good relationship.
It depends on how מקפיד Makpid your in-laws are.
All right. והשתא דאמר רב חסדא מחלוקת בסעודה שנייה. v’Hashta d’Amar Rav
Chisda Machlokes b’Seuda Shniya. Now that רב חסדא Rav Chisda has clarified
that they’re only debating the question of a second meal that used
to be done in the father-in-law’s house. אבל בסעודה ראשונה דברי הכל
מצווה, Aval b’Seuda Rishona Divrei Hakol Mitzvah, but the first meal everybody
agrees is a מצווה. Mitzvah. Again it’s interesting like it doesn’t become
just so entrenched as a מנהג Minhag that then it gets on,
you know, this quality of a מצווה. Mitzvah. Do we really think
that the word מצווה Mitzvah means at one time חז"ל Chazal actually,
you know, sort of like formulated a, you know, like legislated and
said we are now saying this is a מצווה, Mitzvah, or is
it a מצווה Mitzvah sort of in some deep experiential way? So
it’s a little bit unclear, you know, how this sort of evolved.
But nevertheless he says that everybody agrees the first one is a
מצווה, Mitzvah, but the debate is the second. אפילו תימא הא והא
רבי יהודה. Afilu Teima Ha v’Ha Reb Yehuda. So actually both משנה
Mishnah and ברייתא Baraita could be רבי יהודה. Reb Yehuda. ולא קשיא
הא בסעודה ראשונה הא בסעודה שנייה. v’Lo Kashya Ha b’Seuda Rishona Ha
b’Seuda Shniya. The משנה Mishnah that says it’s a מצווה Mitzvah סעודה
ראשונה, Seuda Rishona, the ברייתא Baraita that it’s a רשות Reshus is
the second. We don’t have modern equivalents
so we don’t really have אירוסין. Erusin.
תניא, Tanya, so we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita, אמר רבי יהודה
אני לא שמעתי אלא סעודת אירוסין. Amar Reb Yehuda Ani Lo Shamati
Ela Seudas Erusin. When is it? Now this ברייתא Baraita directly supports
the statement that רב חסדא Rav Chisda has just made that when
is it, when have I heard this idea that it’s a מצווה
Mitzvah the סעודה, Seuda, that’s the סעודה Seuda of אירוסין. Erusin. אבל
לא סבלונות. Aval Lo Sivlonos. Not the סבלונות, Sivlonos, thank you, I’m
just pronouncing it a little yeshivish. סבלונות. Sivlonos. The סבלונות Sivlonos were
gifts that were sent and apparently that they would have that when
they would, and this would be the סעודה שנייה, Seuda Shniya, which
would be that after you’ve had your first meal at your father-in-law’s
house, you send a lot of nice gifts and maybe a lot
of nice food items and you send them to your father-in-law’s house,
and then you go back the second night and you have a
second meal and now it’s a meal eating in your father-in-law’s house
but the gifts that you have sent. So that’s the second meal.
So he says that second meal isn’t a
מצווה. Mitzvah. אמר רבי יוסי אני שמעתי סעודת אירוסין וסבלונות Amar Reb
Yosi Ani Shamati Seudas Erusin v’Sivlonos that both of them are considered
a סעודת מצווה. Seudas Mitzvah. תניא, Tanya, we taught in a ברייתא,
Baraita, רבי שמעון אומר, Reb Shimon Omer, now that we’re talking about
a סעודת מצווה, Seudas Mitzvah, we move and we’re also talking about
weddings, we’re going to have a little אגדתא Agadata about both.
Okay, so תניא, Tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita, רבי שמעון
אומר כל סעודה שאינה של מצווה, Reb Shimon Omer Kol Seuda she'eina
shel Mitzvah, any סעודה Seuda that’s not a סעודת מצווה, Seudas Mitzvah,
אין תלמיד חכם רשאי ליהנות ממנה. Ein Talmid Chacham rishai l’henos mimena.
A תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham cannot derive pleasure from it. Presumably that
doesn't... Presumably that doesn't mean you can't sit down for breakfast or
lunch if it's not a סעודת מצוה. seudas mitzvah. Presumably it means
that if you're going some place, right, either it means to indulge
or if it doesn't mean to indulge, it means that you are
benefiting from somebody else's largesse. That if I am saying, oh, you
know, come not like I assume it's not talking about like a
normal type of a friendly thing. I go to your house for
שבת Shabbos you come to my house, but we're talking about like
a party and I'm inviting people and you're תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham,
so it's not appropriate for you to benefit. Now why is that?
Well let's read a little bit more in the גמרא, Gemara, but
one could speculate one of two things. One is because it's, you
know, it's just a question about sort of an indulgence in physical
pleasures, so and that particularly works if we're talking about a certain
type of ליהנות le-henot means to indulge. It could also sort of
be about the idea of, you know, about your status as a
תורה Torah sage and how much are you do you are you
consciously you know sort of leveraging that or allowing it to be
used as sort of like קרדום לחפור בה. kardom lachpor bah. You
know, so you're getting invited to all of these all of these
parties and all of people's you know and all of people's סעודות,
seudos, is that appropriate for you, you know, because if it's coming
because of you know you could argue דאדרבה de-adarabba it is appropriate,
let them show their respect for me, I'm a תלמיד חכם talmid
chacham and so on. But it could be a two-edged sword.
Very very quickly that person could be out every night of the
week.
That's also true. And the גמרא Gemara is going to get to
that as well and it takes you away from your and it
you know it leads you astray etc. So on the one hand
there's גמרות Gemaros that very much talk about the responsibility of people,
particularly wealthy people to support תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, you know, but
this might again be talking about not just simply putting food on
the table but something of greater of greater largesse.
Even then the question is and should I be let's say I'm
the one who's not the חכם, chacham, I'm throwing it. Should I
be doing that? You know, indulgence and whatever, even better...
I know. So alright, well we'll see today about different standards of
the גמרא. Gemara. So anyway let's take a look. כגון מאי, Kegon
mai, what would be an example about this? What's an example not
of a סעודה שאינה של מצוה? seudah she-eina shel mitzvah? אמר רבי
יוחנן כגון בת כהן לישראל ובת תלמיד חכם לעם הארץ. Amar Rabbi
Yochanan kegon bat kohen le-Yisrael u-vat talmid chacham le-am ha-aretz. So we're
talking about a wedding feast maybe a סעודת אירוסין seudas eirusin or
סעודת נישואין, seudas nisuin, but it's problematic. It's not you know technically
it's a מצוה mitzvah but it's not really appropriate in the eyes
of the גמרא, Gemara, which is a בת כהן bat kohen married
to a ישראל. Yisrael. The גמרא Gemara thinks that כהנים kohanim should
marry among within themselves and the daughter of a תלמיד חכם talmid
chacham marry an עם הארץ am ha-aretz and if you're a תלמיד
חכם talmid chacham you should marry off your daughter to another to
a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. We'll see about that in a minute.
But the עם הארץ am ha-aretz is taking a step up there.
Right, well that's true. דאמר רבי יוחנן בת כהן לישראל אין זיווגן
עולה יפה. De-amar Rabbi Yochanan bat kohen le-Yisrael ein zivugan oleh yafeh.
If a בת כהן bat kohen marries a ישראל, Yisrael, the the
marriage won't turn out so well. מאי היא? Mai hi? What does
that mean? אמר רב חסדא או אלמנה או גרושה או זרע אין
לה, Amar Rav Chisda o almanah o gerushah o zera ein lah,
which is pretty heavy. Right, playing off the פסוק, pasuk, because the
פסוק pasuk says ובת כהן כי תהיה לאיש זר היא בתרומת הקדשים
לא תאכל. U-vat kohen ki tihyeh le-ish zar hi bi-trumat ha-kodashim lo
tochel. And then it says ובת כהן כי תהיה אלמנה וגרושה וזרע
אין לה ושבה אל בית אביה כנעוריה. U-vat kohen ki tihyeh almanah
u-gerushah ve-zera ein lah ve-shavah el beit aviah ki-neureiha. So it's juxtaposed
in the פסוקים, psukim, speaks about her marrying a ישראל Yisrael then
it speaks about if she becomes divorced or widowed or she has
no kids etc., or and she has no kids and so on.
So that's pretty harsh. במתניתא תנא, Be-matnisa tana, in a ברייתא braita
we taught קוברה או קוברתו. kovrah o koverato.
Is this marriage either either he'll bury her or she'll bury him.
I mean in most marriages it's that way, somebody dies first. But
רש״י Rashi says, but רש״י Rashi says it means that they die
that one of them dies early dies before his or her time.
So how much of this is metaphorical?
I don't know. או מביאתו לידי עניות, O mevi'ato lidei aniyut,
or will bring him to poverty. That could be because the כהנים
kohanim were the aristocracy. So therefore it could be a concern that
you know she's used to a higher standard of living. So that's
the one at least that you know at least might have some
practical we can understand practically where that's coming from. איני? Ini? Is
this really true? והאמר רבי יוחנן הרוצה שיתעשר, Ve-ha-amar Rabbi Yochanan ha-rotzeh
she-yitasher, if somebody wants to become rich, ידבק בזרעו של אהרן. yidbak
be-zaro shel Aharon. Like you said it's a step up for the
other side. So if you want to become rich marry somebody marry
you know a כהן kohen or maybe a בת כהן. bat kohen.
כל שכן
שתורה וכהונה מעשרתן, Kol she-ken she-Torah u-khunah measheran,
certainly because if you're a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and you're marrying
a בת כהן, bat kohen, so you'll have both the תורה Torah
and the כהונה kehunah that'll help make you rich. So the גמרא
Gemara says לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא בתלמיד חכם
הא בעם הארץ. Ha be-talmid chacham ha be-am ha-aretz. So we get
back to the תלמיד חכם talmid chacham hierarchy which was the second
part, a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham marrying an עם הארץ. am ha-aretz.
So here you have oh, a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham is allowed
to marry a בת כהן. bat kohen. Then you have like the
two aristocracy. And the way you think about it that's what it
is, right? It's the temple aristocracy and the post-temple aristocracy was the
being a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. So those two aristocracy can marry
amongst themselves. But if you have somebody crossing those lines, a בת
כהן bat kohen marrying an עם הארץ am ha-aretz or a תלמיד
חכם talmid chacham marrying an עם הארץ, am ha-aretz, now we've got
problems.
Well I mean wait but there were two cases. One was בת
כהן לישראל. bat kohen le-Yisrael. The other was בת תלמיד חכם לעם
הארץ. bat talmid chacham le-am ha-aretz.
I know so now בת כהן לישראל bat kohen le-Yisrael winds up
meaning בת כהן לעם הארץ. bat kohen le-am ha-aretz.
ישראל עם הארץ. Yisrael am ha-aretz. Okay because that's to marry out
of all the aristocracies. There's two aristocracies, the כהונה kehunah and the
תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. And the problem is when you marry... outside
of that. You're from the aristocracy and you marry outside. So תלמיד
חכם, Talmid Chacham, so right, could a תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham marry
a בת כהן עם הארץ? Bat Kohen Am Ha'aretz? Maybe. Okay.
No, but isn't there also just two groups or is it just
like עם הארץ Am Ha'aretz versus תלמיד חכם, Talmid Chacham, let's say?
I know, there's a whole range in between. So it could be,
you're, you could be right. Could be that by the כהן Kohen
it's a problem even if it's in the range between תלמיד חכם
Talmid Chacham and עם הארץ. Am Ha'aretz. That you are correct about
that. Okay.
רבי יהושע נסיב כהנתא. Rabbi Yehoshua nasiv kahnata. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
married a בת כהן. Bat Kohen. Notice by the way the shift
from בת כהן Bat Kohen to a כהנת, Kohenet, okay, the use
of the feminine. So again, בת כהן Bat Kohen reflects a patriarchy.
So you even refer to the, to the women by reference to
their fathers. But it is interesting here in the Aramaic, it starts,
it feminizes it. He married a כהנת. Kohenet. חלש, Chalash, he got
sick and he thought that it had to do with the fact
that he did this. So אמר Amar he said, לא ניחא ליה
לאהרן דאדבק בזרעיה? lo nicha leh l'Aharon d'idbak b'zarei? Is it not,
does אהרן Aharon not want me to cleave to his seed, his
descendants, דהוה ליה חתנא כי אנא? dahavei leh chasna ki ana? He
doesn't want to have a son-in-law like me? Is this why I'm
getting sick? I would think I would be good son-in-law material even
for אהרן Aharon's and אהרן Aharon's family. So again the idea that
a תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham with a בת כהן Bat Kohen is
okay. Or at least that was his complaint. כי אנא, Ki ana,
rather רב אידי בר אבין נסיב כהנתא. Rav Idi bar Avin nasiv
kahnata. רב אידי בר אבין Rav Idi bar Avin married a כהנת.
Kohenet. נפק מיניה תרי בני סמיכי. Nafak minei try bnei smichi. And
he from him came, notice from him not from her anyway, two
children who had סמיכה, smicha, meaning two children who had, you know,
who really were big תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim and actually got,
you know, became rabbinical authorities. רב ששת בריה דרב אידי ורב יהושע
בריה דרב אידי. Rav Sheshet brei d'Rav Idi v'Rav Yehoshua brei d'Rav
Idi. רב ששת Rav Sheshet and רב יהושע Rav Yehoshua the son
of
רב אידי. Rav Idi. אמר רב פפה, Amar Rav Papa, אילו לא...
ilu lo... right, for רב ששת? Rav Sheshet? Right. That's not the
רב ששת Rav Sheshet who always comes across as...
I don't think so. אילו לא נסיבנא כהנתא, Ilu lo nasivna kahnata,
had I not married a כהנת, Kohenet, לא איעתרתי, lo itatri, I
would not have become rich. So again, it's a good idea to
marry a כהנת Kohenet especially if you're a תלמיד חכם. Talmid Chacham.
אמר רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, said רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, אילו
לא נסיבנא כהנתא, ilu lo nasivna kahnata, had I not married a
כהנת, Kohenet, לא גלאי, lo galai, I wouldn't have gone into גלות.
galut. Because he act... so here actually this is the counterpoint. He
says actually I got punished like the first story. The first story
he was complaining that he got punished. But here too, oh, I
married a כהנת Kohenet and I got punished, I went into גלות.
galut. So there's a whole story about רב כהנא Rav Kahana having
to run away from בבל Bavel to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. It's
actually interesting, his גלות galut was he was exiled from בבל Bavel
and he had to run to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. But anyway,
so אמרו ליה amru leh they said to him, I said, I'm
sorry, רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. What'd I say, רב פפה? Rav Papa?
רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. אמרו ליה Amru leh they said to him,
והא למקום תורה גלית. v'ha l'makom Torah galita. Why you complaining? You
ran to a place of תורה, Torah, you went to ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, you learned in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. He says no,
לא גלאי כדגלי אינשי, lo galai k'degali inshi, but nevertheless it was
not... not by choice. I was forced to. Okay, he got in
trouble with the Roman, with the government, etc, etc. Okay. So actually,
right. So, but so now there's an interesting thing though because תוספות
Tosafot says that it sounds like רב כהנא Rav Kahana wasn't a
כהן Kohen because he sounds like bad things happened to him because
he married a בת כהן. Bat Kohen. Which by the way could
happen because let's remember כהנא Kahana is a first name, not a
last name. They didn't go by a... what's it called? A patronym?
What's the... a last name. Patronym, right, which is the names we
have, our last names that are handed down by the father. So
that's why for us, כהנא Kahana and כהן Cohen and whatever we
assume the person's a כהן. Kohen. For him it was a first
name. But still the interesting for a ישראל Yisrael to name her
son כהנא. Kahana. But תוספות Tosafot says from this it sounds like
רב כהנא Rav Kahana was not a כהן. Kohen. He says that's
why I got in trouble for marrying a בת כהן. Bat Kohen.
חברותא Chavruta I had in ישראל Yisrael many years back and close
to three decades is now a ר"מ Ram at גוש. Gush. People
know, some people know, was יצחק כהן Yitzchak Cohen who isn't a
כהן. Kohen. So he actually says, he says, I would tell people,
אין כהנא כהן. ein Kahana Kohen. So...
so אין כהנא כהן ein Kahana Kohen also. So anyway. All right.
So he says yes, and
I'm sure the matchmaker, like you know, not try to set up
a ישראל Yisrael with a כהן... Kohen... I mean like...
I don't know what to tell you Michael. So the
גמרא Gemara says... okay. אמר רבי יצחק. Amar Rabbi Yitzchak. We don't
tend to worry about this nowadays. Although I am sure there are
some כהנים Kohanim families that are מקפיד. makpid. Okay. אמר רבי יצחק.
Amar Rabbi Yitzchak. כל הנהנה... kol hanehena... now we get back... so
that's defining what's a סעודה שאינה של מצוה. seudah she'einah shel mitzvah.
Which I want to now go back and say that now that
it's defined that way, the problem might less be about indulgence or
taking advantage of your תורה Torah status and it might be about
somehow implicitly condoning what the רבנים Rabbanim are saying are inappropriate marriages.
It sort of shifts the question of what the problem is. If
we're saying you shouldn't be נהנה מסעודה שאינה של מצוה, nehena mi'seudah
she'einah shel mitzvah, which means a סעודה seudah of a this type
of a bad match, maybe part of the problem is you don't
want to show rabbinic you know sort of as if the רבנים
Rabbanim are sanctioned to this type of a match.
It means that they appropriate the term מצוה mitzvah here in a
different sense. It's a... מצוה mitzvah is not technical. Not technical.
Right. Not technically מצוה. mitzvah. Technically it is a מצוה קידושין mitzvah
kiddushin but it's not something that like we approve of. Exactly.
So we see that phenomenon today. Words are
appropriated to... דעת תורה.
Daas
Torah. Exactly. Exactly. Exactly. Okay. So now אמר רבי יצחק כל הנהנה
מסעודת הרשות. Amar Rabbi Yitzchak kol hanehena mi'seudat ha'reshut. Now now that
sounds like we're going back to the simple מצוה mitzvah point. Are
you going to a wedding meal? That's okay. Are you going to
סתם stam a party or something? or something like that, that's not
acceptable. Okay. כל הנהנה. kol haneheneh. Right, and good point also, it's
not just a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. כל הנהנה מסעודת הרשות, kol
haneheneh miseudas hareshus, לסוף גולה. lesof goleh. And we end up going
to, and it really gets back on the emphasis of
indulgence, שנאמר, she-ne'emar, as the verse says, ואוכלים כרים מצאן ועגלים מתוך
מרבק, v'ochlim karim mitzon va'agalim mitok marbek, and they eat these calves
and these juicy sheep. וכתיב, uch-tiv, and then the next verse says—what
does
מרבק marbek mean?
The, what do you call it, the barn? Or
וכתיב לכן עתה יגלו בראש גולים, uch-tiv lachen ata yiglu berosh golim,
and therefore now they will go into exile at the head of
the exiles. You see, we were so indulgent and now they have
to go into exile. So that clearly is a concern about indulgence.
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
You with the fact that the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was destroyed,
right?
Well, that's not—yes, obviously there was more going on in those פסוק
pasuk about look, things have been so wonderful and now you're going
into exile, but it also is a little bit of censuring in
saying you were, you overly indulged. So there is some of that
message there. All right, let's hold off on the questions, let's hold
off on the questions a little bit because we're a little behind.
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. כל תלמיד חכם המרבה סעודתו בכל מקום. kol
talmid chacham hamarbeh seudato bechol makom. Now we have any תלמיד חכם
talmid chacham that has a large meal in every place. So it's
not exactly נהנה neheneh from a סעודה שאינה של מצוה, seudah she-einah
shel mitzvah, but it's a similar idea about overindulgence, excess, right? And
here it might just be about quantity. Not like you're going out
for sushi and the carved meat every night or whatever like they
have at the wedding shmorg. No, but you just eat a lot
and you're in all places. So meaning you do it as a
very regular thing. סוף מחריב את ביתו, sof machriv et beito, you
will destroy your house. ומאלמן את אשתו, um'almen et ishto, you'll turn
your wife into a widow.
ומייתם את גוזליו, um'yatem et gozalav, you will turn your children, your
chicks into orphans. ותלמודו משתכח ממנו, v'talmudo mishtakeach mimeno, and your תורה
Torah will be forgotten. Basically the point is that you'll be drawn
after the food and you'll be taken away from your תורה. Torah.
So A, it'll undercut your ability to succeed in תורה. Torah. B,
you'll have to support your habit, right? They didn't have cocaine habits
that had to be supported, but you'll have to support your eating
habit. Okay, and you're going to destroy your whole household. Okay, and
this sounds crazy, this sounds crazy, but we know exactly things like
this happen. People doing very well and they get addicted to alcohol
or drugs or whatever and they entirely destroy everything because of their
pursuing their habit.
So ומחלוקות
רבות באות עליו, u-machlokot rabot ba-ot alav, many fights surround you
because you're not putting food on the table, you're not earning a
living, etcetera.
Or רש"י Rashi says, or your creditors, your creditors are coming after
you. ודבריו אינם נשמעים, u-devarav einam nishmayim, nobody listens to you anymore
because they can't trust your תורה Torah anymore. ומחלל שם שמים, um-chalel
shem shamayim, and you desecrate the name of heaven by the type
of behavior you're demonstrating.
ושם רבו ושם אביו, v'shem rabo v'shem aviv, and you bad repute
on your teacher, on your father. וגורם שם רע לו ולבניו ולבני
בניו עד סוף כל הדורות, v'goreim shem ra lo u-levanav u-levnei vanav
ad sof kol hadorot, and now you will create your own bad
reputation and you'll pass it down to all future generations. Very, very
heavy, okay? But clearly there was some type of a phenomenon there
that they were responding to. You know, and I don't know, you
do sometimes see it even today, rabbis that really seem like they're
a little bit too much going after the food and too indulgent.
So מאי היא? mai hee? What does it mean that you'll inherit
that this bad reputation passed down to your future generations? אמר אביי,
Amar Abaye, קרו ליה, karu lei, בר מיכם תנורי. bar meicham tanurei.
You'll get the name of, oh, people will call the children, you'll
say, "Oh, you're the son of the
oven-warmer," the guy who always would be hovering right around the ovens
waiting for the food to come out. רבא אמר, Rava amar, בר
מרקד בי כובי. bar meraked be kubei. They'll call you the son
of the jester, of the person that would do the dances
in the inns. Because if you don't have any money and you
don't have any talents, so what do you do? You have to
act like the jester in order to put food on the table.
רב פפא אמר, Rav Pappa amar, בר מלחך פינכי. bar melachech pinchei.
They'll call you son of the
bowl-licker. רב שמעיה אמר, Rav Shemaya amar, בר מחרבא. bar machrava. They'll
call you son of the person who folds and lies down, like
the person who would lie in the street on his garments because
he couldn't pay the rent. Okay, so very, very heavy. Clearly they
were concerned about a certain phenomenon.
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. לעולם ימכור אדם כל מה שיש לו. leolam
yimkor adam kol ma sheyesh lo. So now we sort of focused
on the intersection between marrying an inappropriate match, תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
to אינו תלמיד חכם eino talmid chacham or כהן kohen or non-כהן
kohen and that and about
having indulgence in a סעודה, seudah, in a סעודת רשות seudat hareshut
or general indulgence. So now we shift back the focus specifically to
the issue of the match and the appropriate versus inappropriate match. תנו
רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. לעולם ימכור אדם כל מה שיש לו, leolam yimkor
adam kol ma sheyesh lo, a person should always sell everything he
has, וישא בת תלמיד חכם, v'yisa bat talmid chacham, and marry the
daughter of a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. Presumably they're talking to תלמידי
חכמים talmidei chachamim and to this rabbinic class, שאם מת או גולה,
she-im met o goleh, because if you die—right, אם מת או גולה
יפה—right, im met o goleh yafeh because if
you
die... You know, you might not always be around. You might die.
You might actually have to travel for a living. Who's going to
make sure your kids get a תורה Torah education? So you better
marry a בת תלמיד חכם, bat talmid chacham, somebody who cares, not
only it means that she has the education herself to pass down,
which maybe it means, but it also means she shares those as
core values in, you know, in the life, in her life, in
your, in your married life. So, אם עשה כן מובטח לו שבניו
תלמידי חכמים, im asah ken muvtach lo shebanav talmidei chachamim, you can
be certain that your kids will get those same values and therefore
will get the sacrifice to make sure that they get a good
Jewish education. Okay. ואל ישא בת עם הארץ, ve'al yisa bat am
ha'aretz, don't marry the daughter of an עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. She
might say, "Oh, not a big deal, I'll make sure they get
the תורה Torah education." You know what? If you're not around, בניו
עמי הארץ, banav amei ha'aretz, nobody is going to make sure, invest
to make sure if you're not around that they get a תורה
Torah education, and they'll turn out to be עמי הארץ. amei ha'aretz.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabanan, לעולם ימכור אדם כל מה שיש לו. le'olam
yimkor adam kol mah sheyesh lo. By the way, this is nice,
I mean, it's harsh, but it's still nice because it makes it
not just about like aristocracy and hierarchy and oh, we don't mingle
with those types, you know, the גמרא Gemara before about not marrying
a בת עם הארץ. bat am ha'aretz. It shows that there was
very practical concerns about what types of values are going to be
taught and passed down within the house.
Okay. לעולם ימכור אדם כל מה שיש לו, le'olam yimkor adam kol
mah sheyesh lo, a person should sell everything he has, וישא בת
תלמיד חכם, veyisa bat talmid chacham, and marry the daughter of a
תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, וישיא בתו לתלמיד חכם, veyasi bito letalmid chacham,
or you should make, if you have a daughter to marry off,
you should make sure she marries a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. Same
point. משל לענבי הגפן בענבי
הגפן דבר נאה ומתקבל. mashal le'invei hagefen be'invei hagefen davar na'eh umitkabel.
Right. So now you know where he gets it from. The grapes
of the vine, you know, the berries of the vine with the
berries of the vine, the grapes of the vine with the grapes
of the vine, it is a beautiful thing and it is and
it's accepted, you know, pleasing to people. ולא ישא בת עם הארץ,
velo yisa bat am ha'aretz, and you should not have a תלמיד
חכם talmid chacham marry the daughter of an עם הארץ. am ha'aretz.
משל, mashal, what would that be like? לענבי הגפן בענבי הסנה, le'invei
hagefen be'invei hasneh, like mixing the berries of the vine, the grapes,
with the berries of a thornbush. דבר כעור ואינו מתקבל. davar ka'ur
ve'eino mitkabel. It is a disgusting thing that does not find favor
in people's eyes. I don't know why you never hear that song
at the weddings, ענבי הגפן בענבי הסנה. invei hagefen be'invei hasneh. No,
somehow
not. Anyway. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabanan, לעולם ימכור אדם כל מה שיש
לו, le'olam yimkor adam kol mah sheyesh lo, person should always sell
everything he, he says sell everything he owns, וישיא בתו. veyasi bito.
By the way, the selling everything you own, I do want to
point out because we were talking about insuring your kids get the
education, you know, in a way, this גמרא Gemara refers to the
high cost of Jewish education. I mean, and you know, the type
of sacrifice you have to make to ensure that תורה Torah gets
passed on to your kids because that's what it's saying: sell everything
to make sure you have the match that's going to ensure that
תורה Torah gets passed on to your kids. כל מה שיש לו
וישא בת תלמיד חכם, kol mah sheyesh lo veyisa bat talmid chacham,
and marry the daughter of a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. לא מצא
בת תלמיד חכם, lo matza bat talmid chacham, if you didn't find
the daughter of a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, nobody, you know, nobody
was around in your city that was a daughter or or the
daughters of the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim were all taken or nobody
was interested in you,
ישא בת גדולי הדור. yisa bat gedolei hador. Try to marry—so now
we get the hierarchy. After תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, and this gets
to Michael's point as well, that there's a huge gap between תלמיד
חכם talmid chacham and עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. I actually did overstate
it before because it says when like a בת כהן bat kohen
can marry a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, you know, there's this whole
range of עם הארץ am ha'aretz that's also seen, of in between
that and עם הארץ am ha'aretz that would also be seen as
inappropriate. Anyway, here, so who's the next people we're listing are not
תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim but presumably they're not עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz
either and they're in this huge middle range. Okay. So, if you
can't find a בת תלמיד חכם, bat talmid chacham, ישא בת גדולי
הדור, yisa bat gedolei hador, marry the daughter of one of the
greats of the generation. Probably means like a civil leader, okay, a
political leader. לא מצא בת גדולי הדור, lo matza bat gedolei hador,
if
you do not find
one of those, רש"י אומר במעשים טובים וצדיקים. Rashi omer bema'asim tovim
utzadikim. Yeah, that's true. Right. But based on the next one, that's
probably more the פשט, pshat, but you're right. רש"י Rashi says it
means people of great of great deeds. לא מצא בת גדולי הדור,
lo matza bat gedolei hador, if you do not find one of
those, ישא בת ראשי כנסיות, yisa bat rashei kenesiyot, marry the daughter
of the heads of synagogues. And that we know that, you know,
from archaeology that there's this status called
archisynagogos or something. Anyway, the head of the synagogue, which was a
position of real like, you know, authority and prestige. לא מצא בת
ראשי כנסיות, lo matza bat rashei kenesiyot, if none of them are
available, ישא בת גבאי צדקה, yisa bat gaba'ei tzedakah, marry the daughter
of those that are the overseers of the צדקה tzedakah collection and
distribution. Also positions of presumably both righteousness and
prestige. לא מצא בת גבאי צדקה, lo matza bat gaba'ei tzedakah, ישא
בת מלמדי תינוקות. yisa bat melamdei tinokot. If you can't find those,
then marry the daughter of at least those that are, you know,
that teach in the that teach in the schools of the like
you get a tuition break. Right. It's interesting that the מלמדי תינוקות
melamdei tinokot are not the תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. They have enough
knowledge to be teaching like in the, you know, to be teaching
the kids. They're not huge תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, but at least
they're deeply invested in תורה. Torah. By the way, it is interesting
because if the point was about just making sure your kids get
a good תורה Torah education, you'd think you might want to jump
to the בת מלמדי bat melamdei to the מלמדי תינוקות, melamdei tinokot,
but clearly no, there's also a hierarchy here of some type of,
like I said, of a hierarchy and a prestige. etc. Okay. ולא
ישא בת עם הארץ, V'lo yisa bat am ha-aretz, but certainly you
should not marry the daughter of an עם הארץ. am ha-aretz. Why?
מפני שהן שקץ ונשותיהם שרץ. Mipnei shehein sheketz v'nshoseihem sheretz. So here
you go lovely, talk about you know a שיגץ, sheigetz, right? So
here they're talking about them, not the women, but you know just
have to feminize it, right? So שקץ. sheketz. Anyway, מפני שהן שקץ
Mipnei shehein sheketz they are an abomination ונשותיהם שרץ v'nshoseihem sheretz and
their wives are like you know like vermin.
ועל בנותיהם הוא
אומר V'al b'noteihem hu omer regarding their daughters it says ארור שוכב
עם כל בהמה. Arur shochev im kol behemah. Just say it's a
good thing Rifka isn't here. Cursed is anyone who sleeps with any
animal. So it might mean that the way they have sex is
very animalistic, which we'll go see something in a minute about that.
Or רש״י Rashi says it could just mean that you know they're
ignorant, so they're so it's basically treating them as though yeah they
don't know anything, they're completely ignorant. They're like animals. You know but
of course the like animals does not just mean it's not just
a statement of their intelligence, it gets broadened. I mean and this
is a very challenging and difficult גמרא Gemara because of you know
the types of you know the way you hear attitudes expressed towards
a whole group and um
you know and obviously Jews have been at the receiving end of
that many times. תניא רבי אומר עם הארץ אסור לאכול בשר שנאמר
Tanya Rebbi omer am ha-aretz assur l'echol basar shene'emar an עם הארץ
am ha-aretz isn't allowed to eat meat because it says זאת תורת
הבהמה והעוף. Zot torat habehemah v'ha'of. תורה Torah is connected to בהמה
ועוף. behemah v'of. כל העוסק בתורה מותר לאכול בשר בהמה ועוף וכל
שאינו עוסק בתורה אסור לאכול בשר בהמה ועוף. Kol ha'osek baTorah mutar
l'echol basar behemah v'of v'chol she'eino osek baTorah assur l'echol basar behemah
v'of. So what does that say about everybody who's now becoming vegetarians
or whatever. Anyway, but again you know some type of thing like
this is a privilege that you're entitled to if you're a תלמיד
חכם. talmid chacham. Maybe then it's an interesting conversation with this and
what we said in the עמוד א׳ amud aleph because the עמוד
א׳ amud aleph was about if you're a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
don't don't indulge. But here maybe it's sort of saying yeah but
you can handle it at least if you have a certain amount.
Whereas if you don't, then there's nothing that civilizes it so you
know this becomes even more
animalistic etc. So here's a whole thing about them being like
non-civilized etc. Before we go on and it's going to be a
little like I said challenging the next piece of the גמרא Gemara
emotionally challenging. Anyway, I just have to tell you a funny story
which is I forget who it's said in the name of but
there's a story that you know this big
you know this big תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, this גדול, gadol, was
looking to marry off his daughter so you know and there was
somebody who was very promising
rising תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and there was interest in marrying the
daughter. He says fine he says you know and it looked like
it was everything was going okay. He says okay but let me
I have to give you a פארהער. farher. So he gives him
a פארהער. farher. He gives him the test. He asks him some
very difficult questions and he answers them. So he says he says
you know you did fine. But he says but I want to
ask you another question like you know I want to I want
to give you you know give you another פארהער. farher. So he
says okay he says if you want to give me another פארהער
farher I'm going to give you a פארהער. farher. So he says
what is this why? He says look why are you giving me
a פארהער? farher? Because the תורה Torah says that you have to
marry off your daughter to a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. But by
that right I should have to give you a פארהער farher because
it says that you have to marry a
בת תלמיד חכם. bat talmid chacham. So why don't I ever why
don't I give you a פארהער? farher? Because from your question I
can see whether you're a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham or not. But
if you didn't rely on the first test I'm not going to
rely on it either. Anyway okay this is what passes for humor
in the ישיבות. yeshivot. All right anyway moving on.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this אמר רבי אלעזר עם הארץ
מותר לנוחרו ביום הכיפורים. Amar Rabbi Elazar am ha-aretz mutar l'nochro b'Yom
HaKippurim. You see why I was avoiding going further. Anyway so an
עם הארץ am ha-aretz you can stab him even on יום כיפור
שחל להיות בשבת. Yom Kippur she'chal l'hiyot b'Shabbat. Okay meaning you know
you can murder, you can violate שבת Shabbat and יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. This person is such a threat to society. We hope that
he was being a little
hyperbolic. אמרו לו תלמידיו רבי אמור לשוחטו. Amru lo talmidav Rebbi emor
l'shochto. Why do you use such violent terms? Stab him? Say to
slaughter him? אמר להן זה טעון ברכה וזה אינו טעון ברכה. Amar
lahen zeh ta'un berachah v'zeh eino ta'un berachah. שחיטה shechitah you make
a ברכה berachah for I don't even want there to be any
association. Of course you don't make a ברכה berachah you kill a
person but anyway with that. So you see how extreme they're being.
Were they sitting were they sitting around having this conversation drinking? Maybe.
אמר רבי אליעזר עם הארץ אסור להתלוות עימו בדרך שנאמר
Amar
Rabbi
Eliezer am ha-aretz assur l'hitlavot imo baderech shene'emar you can't accompany him
on the way, you can't go on a trip with him, כי
היא חייך ואורך ימיך. ki hi chayecha v'orech yamecha. It is your
life and the length of your days. על חייו לא חס al
chayav lo chas he doesn't care about his own life he never
bothers learning תורה. Torah. על חיי חבירו לא כל שכן al chayei
chaveiro lo kol sheken how much more so will he not care
about somebody else's well-being and life. אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני Amar
Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani at least it doesn't say that he's actually
actively trying to kill you. Here it just says that he won't
be concerned about helping protect you. אמר רבי יוחנן עם הארץ מותר
לקורעו כדג. Amar Rabbi Yochanan am ha-aretz mutar l'kor'o k'dag. Similar to
killing him on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. You can tear him like
a fish. You can gut him like a fish. אמר רבי שמואל
בר יצחק ומגבו Amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Yitzchak umigabo from his back
because if you want to kill a fish so it doesn't you
know squeal you cut it in its back. So basically that so
again very graphic and disturbing terms. תוספות Tosafot points out you know
that there are many other גמרות Gemarot that are much... much more
nuanced and obviously not approving, but much less harsh, much more accepting
of עמי הארץ. amei ha'aretz. And תוספות Tosafos says that there are
obviously different categories of עם הארץ am ha'aretz and there was one
category which was seen as very virulently anti-חז"ל Chazal
and you know even maybe violently so as we're about to see.
And that we're referring to that, that's the תוספות Tosafos
of אין מחזירין לו אבדתו. Ein machzirin lo aveidato. The end of
that תוספות Tosafos says וניראה לי, v'nir'eh li, the middle, דלא מיירי
במכיר וכופר להכעיס דהוי ליה כמו פקוח נפש דלסטים וחשוד
על הדמים. d'la mairi b'makir v'kofer l'hach'is d'havei lei k'mo pikuach nefesh
d'listim v'chashud al hadamim. And he says in there like there are
different types of, דאיכא הרבה ענייני עם הארץ d'ika harbe inyanei am
ha'aretz he says towards the end. ויש אומרים, V'yesh omrim, if you
look at the end he says, ויש הרבה ענייני עם הארץ v'yesh
harbe inyanei am ha'aretz כדמוכח בסוטה k'dimuchach b'Sotah etc. And nowadays we
even accept עדות eidus from עם הארץ am ha'aretz etc. So let's
get back to the, but anyway it's very extreme, you have to
hope that we're talking A, as hyperbole and B, as for a
very narrow category of the עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. תניא, Tanya, we
taught in a ברייתא, braisa, אמר רבי עקיבא, Amar Rabbi Akiva, כשהייתי
עם הארץ, k'she'hayiti am ha'aretz, when I was an עם הארץ, am
ha'aretz, I can tell you the inside scoop, אמרתי, amarti, I said,
מי יתן לי תלמיד חכם ואנשכנו כחמור, mi yiten li talmid chacham
v'anshchenu k'chamor, I wish I could have a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
in my grasp and I would like bite him like a donkey.
So there again this sort of violent feeling towards the other group
was felt in both ways. The question always is that who's perpetrating
it, right? So אמרו לו, amru lo, you know if you keep
on it becomes like a cycle of violence or cycle of violent
feelings. אמרו לו תלמידיו, Amru lo talmidav, his students said to him,
רבי אמר ככלב, Rebbe emor k'kelev, why did you say like a
donkey? You should've said like a dog. Okay, אמר להם, amar lahem,
he said to them, זה נושך ושובר עצם וזה נושך ואינו שובר
עצם. zeh noshech v'shover etzem v'zeh noshech v'eino shover etzem. No, when
a donkey bites it breaks a bone and that's how much I
hated the תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. תניא, Tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, braisa, היה רבי מאיר אומר, hayah Rabbi Meir omer, Rabbi Meir
used to say, כל המשיא בתו לעם הארץ, kol hamashi bito l'am
ha'aretz, anybody who marries his daughter to an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz,
so back to that, כאילו כפתה ומניחתה לפני ארי. ke'ilu kaftah u'minichtah
lifnei ari. It's like you bind her up and leave her in
front of a lion. So this refers to like the גמרא Gemara
before of ארורים שוכבים עם כל בהמה, arurim shochvim im kol behemah,
here it seems to be, you know, a refrain to the fact
that the way that they have sex is very animalistic and maybe
essentially let's see, מה ארי דורס ואוכל, mah ari dores v'ochel, the
same way a lion tramples and eats, and תוספות Tosafos says like
doesn't even wait for the animal to die, ואין לו בושת פנים,
v'ein lo boshes panim, and does it with no sense of embarrassment
or you know we say maybe like privacy or whatever, אף עם
הארץ מכה ובועל ואין לו בושת פנים. af am ha'aretz makeh u'bo'el
v'ein lo boshes panim. An עם הארץ am ha'aretz will smite and
have sex and do it without any embarrassment. So basically he'll wind
up raping his wife and their whole approach to sexuality is very
violent and animalistic. That's at least through the eyes of the גמרא.
Gemara. תניא, Tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, רבי אליעזר אומר,
Rabbi Eliezer omer, אלמלא אנו צריכים להם, ilmalei anu tzrichim lahem, were
it not that we were, you know, in need of them למשא
ומתן l'masa u'matan for business, so היו הורגים אותנו, hayu horgim osanu,
they would kill us. Now that's a little bit of a funny
phrase because if we weren't in need of them we would've killed
them, either if we weren't in need of them we would kill
them or if they weren't in need of us they would kill
us. So this might be a little euphemistic and sometimes you, you
know, reverse the subject where you don't want to say it. So
it might be like שונאי ישראל sonei Yisrael etc., you know so
it might be what he's trying to say, היינו הורגים אותם, hayinu
horgim osam, I don't know it says, but anyway but basically we
only tolerate them because we have to. תניא, Tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, braisa, רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, כל העוסק בתורה לפני עם
הארץ, kol ha'osek ba'Torah lifnei am ha'aretz, anybody who learns תורה Torah
in the presence of an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, כאילו בא על
ארוסתו בפניו, ke'ilu ba al arusato befanav, it's like you're having sex
with the
עם הארץ am ha'aretz ארוסה arusah in his
presence. Why? שנאמר תורה צוה לנו משה מורשה. shene'emar Torah tzivah lanu
Moshe morashah. The תורה Torah is an inheritance. אל תקרי מורשה אלא
מאורסה. Al tikrei morashah ela me'orasah. Okay, it is a betrothed woman.
So it's funny because you know normally I think people often understand
this that it means you the תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, the תורה
Torah is a betrothed woman to you and if you're having, learning
תורה, Torah, it's like you're being intimate with your beloved in the
presence of an עם הארץ am ha'aretz and that's inappropriate because that
type of an intimacy you share with the תורה Torah is something
that's inappropriate for people that can't appreciate the nature of that relationship
and you know and are outsiders. But רש"י Rashi says not that
way. רש"י Rashi says ארוסתו arusato doesn't mean your betrothed, it means
his betrothed. The תורה Torah really is every person's betrothed, every person
is you know is betrothed to the תורה. Torah. The only problem
is he's not spending any time with his betrothed. So if you're
learning תורה, Torah, it's like you're sleeping with his wife and you're
embarrassing him because you're doing the thing that he knows he should
be doing and you're the one doing it and not him. That's
the way רש"י Rashi reads it which is a very interesting twist
I think on how often this is read. Okay. אמר רבי, Amar
Rebbe, גדולה שנאה ששונאים עמי הארץ לתלמיד חכם, gedolah sinah she'sonim amei
ha'aretz l'talmid chacham, if you look at the end he says, ויש
הרבה ענייני עם הארץ. v'yesh harbe inyanei am ha'aretz. וגדולה שנאה ששונאים
עמי הארץ לתלמיד חכם, v'gedolah sinah she'sonim amei ha'aretz l'talmid chacham, greater
is the hatred that the עם הארץ am ha'aretz has for the
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham יותר משנאה ששונאים עובדי כוכבים את ישראל yoser
misinah she'sonim ovdei kochavim es Yisrael than the hatred that the heathens
have for the Jews. Right, it might be projection. Right and again
even if it's true it's like okay so both sides are perpetrating
the problem. Well we hate them because they hate us. Well we
hate them. Right. It might be projection. Right. And again, even if
it's true, it's like, okay, so both sides are perpetrating the problem.
"Well, we hate them because they hate us. Well, we hate them
because they hate us," you know? Anyway, okay. More than the non-Jews
hate the Jews, ונשותיהם יותר מהם, vneshoseihem yoter mehem, and their wives
are even more virulent in their hatred. תניא, Tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, braisa, I'm just going to read a little bit more,
שנה ופירש יותר מכולם. shana uperesh yoter mikulam. Somebody who has learned
Torah and left the world of Torah, he is worse than the
than somebody who grew up as an עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. Now,
you could sort of say that it's because he feels guilty because
of what he left etc., but רש"י Rashi says no. No, no,
רש"י Rashi says, because he's heard all the nasty things we say
about them! So, since he's heard all the nasty things we say
about them, he hates us even more than than people that have
never been part of our community hate
us. תנו, Tanu, we תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, our rabbis taught, ששה
דברים נאמרו בעמי הארץ. shisha devarim neemru be'amei ha'aretz. Six things are
said about an עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. אין מוסרים להם עדות, ein
mosrim lahem edus, you don't call them to be עדים edim for
a document. אין מקבלים ממנו עדות. ein mekabelim mimenu edus. Wait, what's
the difference between that and
the first one? The first one is is that you basically say,
I need witnesses for this for this contract, come over. The other
thing is is that they say, oh, we saw ראובן Reuven borrow
a hundred dollars from שמעון. Shimon. Okay. ואין מגלים להם סוד, v'ein
megalim lahem sod, don't tell them a secret, ואין ממנים אותם, v'ein
memanim osam, basically, you can't trust them is the basic point here.
ואין ממנים אותם אפוטרופוס על יתומים, v'ein memanim osam apitropus al yesomim,
don't make them like like what's it called? What's a guardian? Guardian,
right, a guardian for the estate of the orphans, you don't want
an executor of their estate to be responsible for their money. ואין
ממנים אותם אפוטרופוס על קופת צדקה, v'ein memanim osam apitros shel kupas
tzedaka, and don't put them over the distribution of funds. Okay, basically
you can't you can't trust them. ואין מתלווים עמהם בדרך, v'ein mislavim
imahem baderech,
don't accompany them on the way, maybe they'll like rob from you
or so on. ויש אומרים אף אין מכריזים על אבדתו. v'yesh omrim
af ein machrizim al aveidaso. And some say you don't even announce
their אבדה, aveida, you don't return an אבדה. aveida. Of course, תוספות
Tosafos says, if it's an אבדה, aveida, how do you know who
lost it? So תוספות Tosafos says, well, you found it like in
a city in in in a neighborhood of עמי הארץ. amei ha'aretz.
Okay, so you know it has to be an עם הארץ am
ha'aretz who probably lost it.
And the reason why you don't return what? Because they stole it?
And is that why? I mean... Yeah, that's a good question. Basically,
they're חשוד chashud on all issues of money, so some sense of
they don't deserve it or it's not theirs. ותנא קמא, v'tana kamma,
and the תנא קמא tana kamma who says you would return their
אבדה, aveida, זימנין דנפיק מיניה זרע מעליא. zimnin d'nafik minei zera ma'alya.
No,
you should return their lost objects, because you know, they might have
good children that actually go on the right path, ואכיל ליה, v'achal
leh, and he'll eat it, he'll benefit from their wealth. So they
you know so you shouldn't begrudge them their property, שנאמר יכין צדיק
ילבש. shenemar yachin tzaddik yilbash. יכין, Yachin, you will prepare, וצדיק ילבש,
v'tzaddik yilbash, and the righteous will will wear it, will wear it.
So so you see by the end, by the way, that, and
this is what תוספות Tosafos says about different עמי הארץ, amei ha'aretz,
we've toned it down a little bit. We're no longer murdering them
and killing them. It's just a question about trusting them, you know,
in monetary issues. Do they have the same level of being able
to be trusted about about money issues and so on? Which still
is making different classes of people, but it's nowhere near the extreme.
So this גמרא Gemara is of the most extreme גמרות Gemaros about
עמי
הארץ, amei ha'aretz, and it's really important, you know, to realize that
תוספות Tosafos has, A, obviously you could, hopefully it's very metaphorical, and
B, that we're talking about, you know, a certain segment of them
and not all of them. Okay. More tomorrow. That was a fun
דף. daf.